Flies. Chapter 10. The Shell and the Glasses. Piggy eyed the advancing figure
carefully. Nowadays he sometimes found that he saw more clearly if he removed
his glasses and shifted the one lens to the other eye, but even through the good
eye after what had happened, Ralph remained unmistakably Ralph. He came now
out of the coconut trees, limping, dirty, with dead leaves hanging from his
shock of yellow hair. One eye was a slit in his puffy cheek, and a great scab had
formed on his right knee. He paused for a moment and peered at the figure on the
platform. "Piggy, are you the only one left?" "There's some little onins. They
don't count. No biggins. Oh, Sam and Eric. They're collecting wood. Nobody
else? Not that I know of." Ralph climbed onto the platform carefully. The coarse
grass was still worn away where the assembly used to sit. The fragile white
conchk still gleamed by the polished seat. Ralph sat down in the grass facing
the chief's seat and the conchk. Piggy knelt at his left and for a long minute there was
silence. At last Ralph cleared his throat and whispered something. Piggy
whispered back. What you say? Ralph spoke up. Simon. Piggy said nothing but
nodded solemnly. They continued to sit, gazing with impaired sight at the
chief's seat and the glittering lagoon.
The green light and the glossy patches of sunshine played over their befouled
bodies. At length, Ralph got up and went to the conchk. He took the shell
caressingly with both hands and knelt, leaning against the trunk.
Piggy, huh? What we going to do? Piggy nodded at the conchk. You could call an
assembly. Ralph laughed sharply as he said the word, and Piggy frowned. You're
still chief. Ralph laughed again. You are over us. I got the conchk. Ralph, stop
laughing like that. Look, there ain't no need, Ralph. What's the others going to
think? At last, Ralph stopped. He was shivering. Piggy. Huh? That was Simon.
You said that before. Piggy. Huh? That was murder. You stop it, said Piggy
Shrillly. What good are you doing talking like that? He jumped to his feet
and stood over Ralph. It was dark. There was that that bloody dance. There was
lightning and thunder and rain. We were scared. I wasn't scared, said Ralph
slowly. I was I don't know what I was.
We was scared, said Piggy excitedly.
Anything might have happened. It wasn't what you said. He was justiculating,
searching for a formula. Oh, Piggy. Ralph's voice, low and stricken,
stopped Piggy's gestures. He bent down and waited. Ralph, cradling the conchk,
rocked himself to and fro. Don't you understand, Piggy? The things we did. He
may still be. No, perhaps he was only pretending. Piggy's voice trailed off at
the side of Ralph's face. You were outside the circle. You never really came in. Didn't you see
what we what they did?
There was loathing, and at the same time a kind of feverish excitement in his
voice. Didn't you see, Piggy? Not all that well. I only got one eye now. You
ought to know that, Ralph. Ralph continued to rock to and fro. It was an
accident, said Piggy suddenly. That's what it was, an accident. His voice
shrilled again. Coming in the dark. He had no business crawling like that out
of the dark. He was baddy. He asked for it. He justiciculated widely again. It
was an accident. You didn't see what they did. Look, Ralph, we've got to
forget this. We can't do no good thinking about it. See, I'm frightened
of us. I want to go home. Oh, God. I want to go home. It was an accident,
said Piggy stubbornly. And that's that.
He touched Ralph's bare shoulder, and Ralph shuddered at the human
contact. And look, Ralph. Piggy glanced round quickly, then leaned close. Don't
let on. We was in that dance. Not to Sam
and Eric. But we were all of us. Piggy shook his head. Not us till last. They
never noticed in the dark. Anyway, you said I was only on the
outside. So was I, muttered Ralph. I was on the outside, too. Piggy nodded
eagerly. That's right. We was on the outside. We never done nothing. We never
seen nothing. Piggy paused, then went on. We'll live on our own. The four of
us. Four of us. We aren't enough to keep the fire burning. We'll try. See, I lit
it. Sam and Eric came, dragging a great log out of the forest. They dumped it by
the fire and turned to the pool. Ralph jumped to his feet. Hi, you two. The
twins checked a moment, then walked on.
They're going to bathe, Ralph. Better get it over. The twins
were very surprised to see Ralph. They flushed and looked past him into the
air. Hello. Fancy meeting you, Ralph. We just been in the forest to get wood for
the fire. We got lost last night. Ralph examined his toes. You got lost after
the Piggy cleaned his lens. After the feast, said Sam in a stifled voice. Eric
nodded. Yes, after the feast. We left early, said Piggy quickly. Because we
were tired. So did we. Very early. We were very tired. Sam touched a scratch
on his forehead and then hurriedly took his hand away. Eric fingered his split
lip. "Yes, we were very tired," repeated Sam, so we left early. "Was it a good?"
The air was heavy with unspoken knowledge. Sam twisted, and the obscene words shot out of him.
"Dance?" Memory of the dance that none of them had attended shook all four boys
convulsively. We left early.
When Roger came to the neck of land that joined the castle rock to the mainland,
he was not surprised to be challenged.
He had reckoned during the terrible night on finding at least some of the
tribe, holding out against the horrors of the island in the safest place. The
voice rang out sharply from on high, where the diminishing crags were
balanced one on another. Halt. Who goes there? Roger. Advance, friend. Roger
advanced. You could see who I was. The chief said we got to challenge everyone.
Roger peered up. You couldn't stop me coming if I wanted. Couldn't I climb up
and see? Roger clambered up the ladlike cliff. Look at this. A log had been
jammed under the topmost rock and another lever under that. Robert leaned
lightly on the lever, and the rock groaned. A full effort would send the rock thundering
down to the neck of land. Roger admired.
He's a proper chief, isn't he? Robert nodded. He's going to take us hunting.
He jerked his head in the direction of the distant shelters where a thread of
white smoke climbed up the sky. Roger, sitting on the very edge of the cliff,
looked somberly back at the island as he worked with his fingers at a loose
tooth. His gaze settled on the top of the distant mountain, and Robert changed
the unspoken subject. He's going to beat Wilfred. What for? Robert shook his head
doubtfully. I don't know. He didn't say.
He got angry and made us tie Wilfrid up.
He's been He giggled excitedly. He's been tied for hours waiting. But didn't
the chief say why? I never heard him.
Sitting on the tremendous rock in the torid sun, Roger received this news as an
illumination. He ceased to work at his tooth and sat still, assimilating the
possibilities of irresponsible authority. Then, without another word,
he climbed down the back of the rocks toward the cave and the rest of the
tribe. The chief was sitting there, naked to the waist, his face blocked out
in white and red. The tribe lay in a semicircle before him. The newly beaten
and untied Wilfred was sniffing noisily in the background. Roger squatted with
the rest. Tomorrow, went on the chief, we shall hunt again. He pointed at this
savage and that with his spear. Some of you will stay here to improve the cave
and defend the gate. I shall take a few hunters with me and bring back meat. The
defenders of the gate will see that the others don't sneak in. A savage raised
his hand, and the chief turned a bleak, painted face toward him. Why should they
try to sneak in, chief? The chief was vague but earnest. They will. They'll
try to spoil things we do, so the watchers at the gate must be careful.
And then the chief paused. They saw a triangle of startling pink dart out, pass along his
lips, and vanish again. And then the beast might try to come in. You remember
how he crawled?" The semicircle shuddered and muttered in agreement. "He
came disguised. He may come again, even though we gave him the head of our kill
to eat. So watch and be careful." Stanley lifted his forearm off
the rock and held up an interrogative finger.
Well, but didn't we? Didn't we? He squirmed and looked down. No. In the
silence that followed, each savage flinched away from his individual
memory. No. How could we kill it? Half relieved, half daunted by the
implication of further terrors, the savages murmured again. "So leave the
mountain alone," said the chief solemnly, "and give it the head if you go hunting."
Stanley flicked his finger again. I expect the beast disguised
itself. Perhaps, said the chief. A theological speculation presented
itself. We'd better keep on the right side of him anyhow. You can't tell what
he might do. The tribe considered this and then were shaken as if by a flow of
wind. The chief saw the effect of his words and stood abruptly. But tomorrow
we'll hunt, and when we've got meat, we'll have a feast. Bill put up his
hand. Chief, yes. What do we use for lighting the fire? The chief's blush was
hidden by the white and red clay. Into his uncertain silence, the tribe spilled
their murmur once more. Then the chief held up his hand. We shall take fire
from the others. Listen. Tomorrow we'll hunt and get meat. Tonight I'll go along
with two hunters. Who will come? Maurice and Roger put up their hands. Maurice.
Yes, chief. Where was their fire? Back at the old place by the fire rock.
The chief nodded. The rest of you can go
to sleep as soon as the sun sets. But us three, Maurice, Roger, and me, we've got
work to do. We'll leave just before sunset. Maurice put up his hand. But
what happens if we meet? The chief waved his objection aside. We'll keep along by
the sands. Then if he comes, we'll do our our dance again. Only the three of
us again. The murmur swelled and died away. Piggy handed Ralph his glasses and
waited to receive back his sight. The wood was damp, and this was the third
time they had lighted it. Ralph stood back, speaking to himself. We don't want
another night without fire. He looked round guilty at the three boys standing
by. This was the first time he had admitted the double function of the
fire. Certainly, one was to send up a beckoning column of smoke, but the other
was to be a hearth now, and a comfort until they slept. Eric breathed on the
wood till it glowed and sent out a little flame. A billow of white and
yellow smoke reaked up. Piggy took back his glasses and looked at the smoke with
pleasure. If only we could make a radio or a plane or a boat. Ralph dredged in
his fading knowledge of the world. We might get taken prisoner by the Reds.
Eric pushed back his hair. They'd be better than he would not name people.
And Sam finished the sentence for him by nodding along the beach. Ralph
remembered the ungainainely figure on a parachute. He said something about a dead man.
He flushed painfully at this admission that he had been present at the dance.
He made urging motions at the smoke and with his body. Don't stop. Go on up.
Smoke's getting thinner. We need more wood already, even when it's wet. My
asthma. The response was mechanical. Sucks to your asthma. If I
pull logs, I get my asthma bad. I wish I didn't, Ralph, but there it is. The
three boys went into the forest and fetched armfuls of rotten wood. Once
more the smoke rose yellow and thick.
Let's get something to eat. Together they went to the fruit trees, carrying
their spears, saying little, cramming in haste. When they came out of the forest
again, the sun was setting and only embers glowed in the fire and there was
no smoke. I can't carry any more wood, said Eric. I'm tired. Ralph cleared his throat. We kept
the fire going up there. Up there it was
small, but this has got to be a big one.
Ralph carried a fragment to the fire and watched the smoke that drifted into the
dust. We've got to keep it going. Eric flung himself down. I'm too tired. And
what's the good, Eric? cried Ralph in a shocked voice. Don't talk like that. Sam
knelt by Eric. Well, what is the good?
Ralph tried indignantly to remember.
There was something good about a fire, something overwhelmingly good. Ralph's
told you often enough, said Piggy moodily. How else are we going to be
rescued? Of course, if we don't make smoke, he squatted before them in the
crowding dusk. Don't you understand?
What's the good of wishing for radios and boats? He held out his hand and
twisted the fingers into a fist. There's only one thing we can do to get out of
this mess. Anyone can play at hunting.
Anyone can get us meat. He looked from face to face. Then, at the moment of
greatest passion and conviction, that curtain flapped in his head, and he
forgot what he had been driving at. He knelt there, his fist clenched, gazing
solemnly from one to the other. Then the curtain whisked back. Oh, yes. So, we've got to make
smoke and more smoke. But we can't keep it going. Look at that. The fire was
dying on them. Two to mind the fire, said Ralph, half to himself. That's 12
hours a day. We can't get any more wood, Ralph. Not in the dark, not at night. We
can light it every morning, said Piggy.
Nobody ain't going to see smoke in the dark. Sam nodded vigorously. It was
different when the fire was up there.
Ralph stood up, feeling curiously defenseless, with the darkness pressing
in. "Let the fire go then, for tonight."
He led the way to the first shelter, which still stood, though battered. The
bed leaves lay within, dry and noisy to the touch. In the next shelter, a little
was talking in his sleep.
The four biggin crept into the shelter and burrowed under the leaves. The twins
lay together and Ralph and Piggy at the other end. For a while there was the continual
creek and rustle of leaves as they tried for comfort. Piggy. Yeah. All right. Suppose
so. At length, say for an occasional rustle, the shelter was silent. An
oblong of blackness relieved with brilliant spangles hung before them, and
there was the hollow sound of surf on the reef. Ralph settled himself for his nightly game of
supposing supposing they could be transported home by jet. Then before
morning they would land at that big airfield in Wiltshire. They would go by
car. No, for things to be perfect they would go by train all the way down to
Devon and take that cottage again. Then at the foot of the garden the wild
ponies would come and look over the wall. Ralph turned restlessly in the
leaves. Dartmore was wild and so were the ponies, but the attraction of
wildness had gone. His mind skated to a consideration of a tamed town where
savagery could not set foot. What could be safer than the bus center with its
lamps and wheels all at once? Ralph was dancing round a lampstandard. There was a bus crawling
out of the bus station, a strange bus.
Ralph, Ralph, what is it? Don't make a noise like that. Sorry. From the
darkness of the further end of the shelter came a dreadful moaning, and
they shattered the leaves in their fear.
Sam and Eric, locked in an embrace, were fighting each other. Sam. Sam. Hey,
Eric. Presently, all was quiet again.
Piggy spoke softly to Ralph. We got to get out of this. What do you mean? Get
rescued. For the first time that day, and despite the crowding blackness,
Ralph sniggered. I mean it, whispered Piggy. If we don't get home soon, we'll
be barmy round the bend. Bomb happy crackers. Ralph pushed the damp tendrils
of hair out of his eyes. You write a letter to your auntie. Piggy considered
this solemnly. I don't know where she is now, and I haven't got an envelope and a
stamp, and there isn't a mailbox or a postman. The success of his tiny joke
overcame Ralph. His sniggers became uncontrollable. His body jumped and
twitched. Piggy rebuked him with dignity. I haven't said anything all
that funny. Ralph continued to snigger, though his chest hurt. His twitchings
exhausted him till he lay breathless and woe be gone, waiting for the next spasm.
During one of these pauses, he was ambushed by sleep. Ralph, you've been
making a noise again. Do be quiet, Ralph. Because Ralph heaved over among
the leaves. He had reason to be thankful that his dream was broken, for the bus
had been nearer and more distinct. Why?
Because. Be quiet and listen.
Ralph lay down carefully to the accompaniment of a long sigh from the
leaves. Eric moaned something and then lay still. The darkness, save for the
useless oblong of stars, was blanket thick. I can't hear anything. There's
something moving outside. Ralph's head prickled. The sound of his blood drowned
all else and then subsided. I still can't hear anything. Listen. Listen for
a long time. quite clearly and emphatically, and only a yard or so away
from the back of the shelter, a stick cracked. The blood roared again in
Ralph's ears. Confused images chased each other through his mind. A composite
of these things was prowling around the shelters. He could feel Piggy's head
against his shoulder and the convulsive grip of a hand. Ralph, Ralph, shut up
and listen. Desperately, Ralph prayed that the beast would prefer Littlein's.
A voice whispered horribly outside.
Piggy, piggy, it's come, gasped Piggy. It's real. He clung to Ralph and reached to
get his breath. Piggy, come outside. I want you, Piggy. Ralph's mouth was
against Piggy's ear. Don't say anything. Piggy, where are you, Piggy?
Something brushed against the back of the shelter. Piggy kept still for a
moment, then. He had his asthma. He arched his back and crashed among the
leaves with his legs. Ralph rolled away from him. Then there was a vicious
snarling in the mouth of the shelter, and the plunge and thump of living
things. Someone tripped over Ralph and Piggy's corner became a complication of
snarls and crashes and flying limbs. Ralph hid out. Then he and what
seemed like a dozen others were rolling over and over, hitting, biting,
scratching. He was torn and jolted.
Found fingers in his mouth and bit them.
A fist withdrew and came back like a piston so that the whole shelter exploded into light.
Ralph twisted sideways on top of a writhing body and felt hot breath on his
cheek. He began to pound the mouth below him. Using his clenched fist as a
hammer, he hit with more and more passionate hysteria as the face became
slippery. A knee jerked up between his legs and he fell sideways, busying
himself with his pain, and the fight rolled over him. Then the shelter
collapsed with smothering finality, and the anonymous shapes fought their way
out and through. Dark figures drew themselves out of the wreckage and
flitted away till the screams of the littles and piggy's gasps were once more
audible. Ralph called out in a quavering voice. All you little go to sleep. We've
had a fight with the others. Now go to sleep. Sam Eric came close and peered at
Ralph. Are you two all right? I think so. I got busted. So did I. How's Piggy?
They hauled Piggy clear of the wreckage and leaned him against a tree. The night
was cool and purged of immediate terror.
Piggy's breathing was a little easier.
"Did you get hurt, Piggy?" "Not much."
"That was Jack and his hunters," said Ralph bitterly. "Why can't they leave us
alone?" "We gave them something to think about," said Sam. Honesty compelled him
to go on. "At least you did. I got mixed
up with myself in a corner." "I gave one of them what for?" said Ralph. "I
smashed him up all right. He won't want to come and fight us again in a hurry."
"So did I," said Eric. "When I woke up,
one was kicking me in the face. I got an awful bloody face, I think, Ralph. But I
did him in the end. What did you do? I got my knee up, said Eric with simple
pride. And I hit him with it in the pills. You should have heard him holler.
He won't come back in a hurry either, so we didn't do too
badly. Ralph moved suddenly in the dark, but then he heard Eric working his
mouth. What's the matter? Just a tooth loose. Piggy drew up his legs. You all
right, Piggy? I thought they wanted the conchk. Ralph trotted down the pale
beach and jumped onto the platform. The conchk still glimmered by the chief's
seat. He gazed for a moment or two, then went back to
Piggy. They didn't take the conchk. I know. They didn't come for the conchk.
They came for something else. Ralph, what am I going to
do? Far off along the bow stave of beach. Three figures trotted toward the
castle rock. They kept away from the forest and down by the water.
Occasionally they sang softly.
Occasionally they turn cartwheels down by the moving streak of phosphoresence.
The chief led then, trotting steadily, exalting in his achievement. He is the
chief now in truth, and he made stabbing motions with his spear. From his left
hand dangled Piggy's broken
glasses, Lord of the